Guide to the Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs ARC.306
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 7: Brownstone Revival Comittee records, 1967-2008
  Additional files related to the BRC can be found in Series 3: Everett and Evelyn Ortner personal papers, Series 5: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation lectures, Series 6: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation general files, Series 8: Back to the City Conference, Series 9: Brownstones and Historic Preservation clippings, and Series 10: Brownstone correspondence.
  Sub-series 7.1: Brownstone Revival Committee administrative records
  Sub-series 7.2: Brownstone Revival Committee lectures, seminars, and workshops
  Sub-series 7.3: The Brownstoner
  Sub-series 7.4: Brownstone calendars and photographs
  Sub-series 7.5: H. Dickson McKenna files
  - Sub-series 7.1: Brownstone Revival Committee administrative records, 1967-2008; 5.85 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes, four folders, and two oversize folder
    The sub-series contains administrative records of the Brownstone Revival Committee (BRC) (later the Brownstone Revival Coalition), dating from 1967 to 2008. They include Board of Directors files, correspondence, reports, financial records, photographs, home-buyer's guides, one scrapbook, and ephemera.
    The BRC organized the first Back to the City conference in 1974, and some files related to that conference are found in this sub-series.
    - BRC Historic, 1967-2004 (Box 26, Folder 10)
      Includes 1979-1986 board meeting minutes
    - Home-Buyer's Guide to New York City Brownstone Neighborhoods, 1969 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - BRC - General I, 1969-1975 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - BRC - General II, 1968-1974 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - BRC - General III, 1970-1986 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - BRC "Gems", 1970s-1998 (Box 27, Folder 3)
      Includes Park Slope walking tour, Gowanus typescript by John Muir, lists of recommended professionals and craftpersons, and other documents
    - BRC vs. IRS, 1970-1971 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Brownstone Surveys, 1971-2002 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Back to the City tour, 1974 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - BRC - Publicity, 1974-1976 (Box 27, Folder 7)
      Includes Back to the City
    - BRC bank, mortgages, and bankers, 1975-1976 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - BRC board meetings, 1977-1983 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Includes financial records
    - BRC Guide to New York City's Fine Old Neighborhoods (fourth edition), 1979 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Brownstone Revival Committee scrapbook, 1979-1980 (Box 77, Folder -)
    - Brownstone Revival Committee and Brownstone Fairs, 1980-1987 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Includes photograph of Brooklyn Borough President Sebastian Leone and Brooklyn Union Gas Company President Eugene Luntey with Brownstone billboard
    - Reverse Mortgages, 1982-1994 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Includes Ortners' reverse mortgage application for 272 Berkeley Place and issues of the Brownstoner (Spring and Winter 1989, Spring 1990, and Fall 1993)
    - Brownstone Revival Coalition of New York, 1982-2007 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Brooklyn Brownstone Fair posters, 1986 (Box 75, Folder -)
    - BRC brochure layout, 1986 (Box 75, Folder -)
    - BRC correspondence, 1986-2000 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Brownstoner Ad appeal/rates, 1986-2004 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Brownstone Awards, 1989-1993 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - BRC membership forms, circa 1990s (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Grants, 1990-1996 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - BRC miscellaneous, 1995-1998 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - BRC Board of Directors, 1996-1997 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - BRC brochure, 1996-2001 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - BRC bills, 1996-2003 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - BRC board meetings and mailing lists, 2008 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Sub-series 7.2: Brownstone Revival Committee lectures, seminars, and workshops, 1970-2004; 0.65 Linear Feet in twelve folders
    The sub-series contains files relating the lectures, workshops, and seminars produced by the Brownstone Revival Comittee (later the Brownstone Revival Coalition), dating from 1970 to 2004. It includes correspondence, flyers, programs, lecture notes, slide lists, and photographs.
    Additional lectures delivered by EHO, some of which may have been produced by the Brownstone Revival Committee, can be found in Sub-series 3.1: Personal papers, memorabilia, and photographs, Sub-series 3.3: Publicity, and Series 5: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation lectures. Slides were used by EHO in his lectures can be found in Sub-series 4.3: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation slides.
    - BRC lectures, 1970-1974 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - BRC lecture notes and slide lists (2 folders), 1970s-2004 (Box 25, Folder 7-8)
    - BRC lecture, "A New Skyline for Brownstone Brooklyn?", 1990-2002 (Box 26, Folder 1, Item digital files)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Donated on one 3.5 inch floppy disk, containing two digital files in .dat and .doc formats. Digital ID arc_306_media_001.
      Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
    - BRC seminars, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - BRC fall seminars, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - BRC workshops, 1980-2001 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - BRC workshop, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - BRC workshop, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - BRC workshop, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - BRC workshop, 1994 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - BRC workshop, 2001 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 7.3: The Brownstoner, 1968-2005; 0.25 Linear Feet in three folders
    The sub-series contains issues of The Brownstoner, the newsletter for the Brownstone Revival Committee (later the Brownstone Revival Coalition), dating from 1968 to 2005. The newsletter includes articles on historic home renovation, state and local legislation concerning historic homes and home buying, finances (mortgages, insurance, etc.), cultural events, street beautification, walking tours and lectures, landmarking, and gentrification.
    - The Brownstoner, 1968-1970 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - The Brownstoner, 1971-1972 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - The Brownstoner, 1973-1974 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - The Brownstoner, 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - The Brownstoner, 1977-1978 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - The Brownstoner, 1979-1980 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - The Brownstoner, 1981-1982 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - The Brownstoner, 1983-1985 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - The Brownstoner, 1986-1987 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - The Brownstoner, 1988-1989 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - The Brownstoner, 1990-1992 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - The Brownstoner, 1993-1997 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - The Brownstoner, 1998-2005 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Sub-series 7.4: Brownstone calendars and photographs, 1985-2006; 0.65 Linear Feet in thirteen folders
    The sub-series is subdivided into calendars and photographs. Each section is arranged chronologically.
    The sub-series consists of calendars produced by the Brownstone Revival Committee (later the Brownstone Revival Coalition) and copy photographs (prints, negatives, and contact sheets) that were featured in the calendars, dating from 1985 to 2006. The calendars include images of 19th century New York (primarily Manhattan) and advertisements for businesses related to brownstones and historic home renovation. The photographs portion of the sub-series includes some images that were not used in the calendars. The sub-series does not include calendars for the following years: 1986, 1987, and 2003.
    Additional copy slides of images used in the calendar can be found in Sub-series 4.3: Brooklyn and Historic Preservation slides.
    - Brownstone calendars, 1985, 1988-1997 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Brownstone calendars, 1998-2002, 2004-2006 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints and negatives, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Includes photograph of EGO and Clem Labine
    - Brownstone calendar - Negatives and contact sheets, 1988 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints and negatives, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Brownstone calendar - Pix not used, 1991 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Brownstone calendar - Negatives, 1991-1992 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints and negatives, 1994-1995 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints and negatives, 1998-1999 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints, negatives, and captions, 2002 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Brownstone calendar - Negatives, 2003 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Brownstone calendar - Prints, 2000s (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Sub-series 7.5: H. Dickson McKenna files, 1972-1994; 1.8 Linear Feet in three folders and one oversize folder
    The sub-series contains the Brownstone Revival Committee (BRC) and Back to the City Conference records of H. Dickson McKenna, dating from 1972 to 1994. McKenna was an organizer and speaker at the first Back to the City Conference in 1974, and served as the Treasurer and board member of the BRC in the 1980s and 1990s.
    - H. Dickson McKenna's Back to the City file, 1972-1974 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - H. Dickson McKenna's BRC board files, 1981-1982 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - H. Dickson McKenna's BRC board files, 1985-1994 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - H. Dickson McKenn'as BRC financial records, 1984-1992 (Box 72, Folder -)
- Series 8: Back to the City Conference records, 1973-1992
  The series contains records relating to the Back to the City Conference (BTTC), dating from 1973 to 1992. It includes the records of the organization (Board of Directors files) and files relating to individual conferences.
  Additional BTTC files can be found in Series 7: Brownstone Revival Comittee, Series 9: Brownstones and Historic Preservation clippings, and Series 10: Brownstone correspondence.
  The series in divided into two sub-series:
  Sub-series 8.1: Back to the City Conference administrative records
  Sub-series 8.2: Back to the City Conference - Annual conferences
  - Sub-series 8.1: Back to the City Conference administrative records, 1973-1992; 5.1 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes, one small box, and one oversize folder
    The sub-series contains administrative records of the Back to the City Conference (BTTC), dating from 1973 to 1992. It includes Board of Directors files, financial records, correspondence, newsletters, and ephemera. It also includes files on conferences and other events where EHO represented BTTC.
    - Back to the City seal, 1970s (Box 69, Item -)
    - BRC foundation appeal, 1970s (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - BTTC stationery, 1970s (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1973-1975 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - BTTC proceedings matters, 1974-1975 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - BTTC leaflet, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation and Rider 8, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - BTTC corporate matters and contracts, 1975-1976 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Documents / Articles, 1975-1976 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - BTTC Board of Directors and Advisory Board correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - BTTC Board of Directors meetings, 1975-1983 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - BTTC Board of Directors minutes and by-laws, 1975-1980 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - National Trust for Historic Preservation, 1975-1979 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - BTTC contacts, 1975-1980 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - BTTC and BRC correspondence, 1975-1986 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to/from preservation organizations, 1975-1986 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - BTTC check book and finances, 1975-1992 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Administrative Code J-51, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - International Downtown Executives Association Mid-Year Conference - Little Rock, Arkansas, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      EHO led BTTC panel
    - BTTC News Reports and literature, 1976-1980 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - BTTC general files, 1976-1985 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - American Institute of Architects - Preservation of Historic Resources conference - Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      EHO spoke at conference
    - Richard Crissman correspondence, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - City Living '78 poster, 1978 (Cabinet Flat file A, Drawer 1)
    - Old House Workshop - Buffalo, New York, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      EHO presented for Back to the City
    - Housing for the Elderly conference - Detroit, Michigan, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      EHO delivered keynote address
    - Preservation Action, 1978-1981 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Columbia proposal, 1979 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - BTTC Board of Directors, 1979-1986 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - EHO Westover School talk, 1980 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Urban Visitors Network, 1981 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - BTTC financial records, 1981-1982 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - BTTC miscellaneous, 1982 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - BTTC Board of Directors meetings, 1982-1983 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - The Townscape Institute, 1983 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Sub-series 8.2: Back to the City Conference - Annual conferences, 1974-1986; 2 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes and two folders
    Arranged chronologically by the date of each conference. The first file in the sub-series contains participant lists from each conference.
    The sub-series contains files on the annual Back to the City Conferences, dating from 1974 to 1986. The files document the organizing and logistics of each conference, and include correspondence, programs, brochures, posters, financial records, press releases, photographs, and ephemera relating to the cities in which the conferences were hosted.
    - BTTC Conference participant lists, 1974-1984 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Back to the City Conference - New York, New York, 1974 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Back to the City Conference - New York, New York press kit, 1974 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Back to the City Conference - St. Paul, Minnesota, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Back to the City Conference - Washington D.C., 1976 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Back to the City Conference - San Antonio, Texas, 1977 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Back to the City Conference - Hartford, Connecticut (2 folders), 1978 (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
      Includes Connecticut Governor Ella Grasso and Hartford Mayor George A. Athanson
    - Back to the City Conference - Louisville, Kentucky (2 folders), 1979 (Box 33, Folder 3-4)
      Includes Louisville Mayor William B. Stansbury
    - Back to the City Conference - Wilmington, Delaware, 1980 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Back to the City Conference - Milwaukee, Wisconsin (2 folders), 1981 (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
    - Back to the City Conference - Milwaukee, Wisconsin - EHO speech, 1981 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - Back to the City Conference - Jim Thorpe, Pennsylvania / Mauch Chunk (2 folders), 1982 (Box 34, Folder 3-4)
    - Back to the City Conference - Brooklyn, New York, 1983 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Back to the City Conference - Brooklyn, New York, 1983 (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Back to the City Conference - Miami Beach, Florida, 1984 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Back to the City Conference - Cleveland, Ohio, 1985 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Back to the City Conference - Cleveland, Ohio (2 folders), 1985 (Box 79, Folder 5-6)
    - Back to the City Conference - Fort Wayne, Indiana, 1986 (Box 79, Folder 7)
- Series 9: Brownstones and Historic Preservation clippings, 1966-1985; 2.3 Linear Feet in three manuscript boxes and one oversize folder
  The series contains clippings relating to brownstones and the historic preservation movement, including the Brownstone Revival Committee (BRC), Back to the City Conference (BTTC), and the Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella project, dating from 1966 to 1985.
  - Brownstone clippings and ephemera (4 folders), 1966-1982 (Box 35, Folder 2-5)
    Includes BRC, BTTC, Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella projects, and Brooklyn Museum
  - EHO stuff - Book (BTTC clippings), 1968-1984 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Historic Preservation articles, 1970s, 2002-2004 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - BTTC / BRC clippings (1-3 of 4 folders), 1974-1979 (Box 36, Folder 2-4)
    Includes some correspondence and ephemera
  - BTTC / BRC clippings (4 of 4), 1974-1979 (Box 73, Folder -)
  - Housing and BTTC clippings, 1975-1982 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Housing clippings, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Housing clippings (3 folders), 1979-1981, 2004 (Box 37, Folder 1-3)
  - BTTC / BRC clippings, 1984-1985 (Box 37, Folder 4)
- Series 10: Brownstone correspondence, 1965-2005; 0.4 Linear Feet in five folders
  The series consists of correspondence relating to brownstones and the urban historic preservation movement, especially in the Park Slope neigborhood of Brooklyn, dating from 1965 to 2005. It includes several organizations, such as the Park Slope Betterment Committee, the Brownstone Revival Committee, and the Back to the City Conference. It also includes several local politicians, such as U.S. Congressman Fred Richmond, U.S. Congresswoman Yvonne B. Burke, U.S. Congressman Leo C. Zefferetti, Mayor Edward I. Koch, and Borough President Howard Golden.
  Of note are letters urging local banks to extend mortgage loans to homebuyers in the previously "red-lined" neighborhood of Park Slope in the 1960s.
  - Brownstone correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Includes Park Slope Betterment Committee
  - Brownstone correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Brownstone correspondence, 1971-1978 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Includes Park Slope Betterment Committee, Brownstone Revival Committee, Back to the City, U.S. Congressman Fred Richmond, and U.S. Congresswoman Yvonne B. Burke
  - Brownstone correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Includes Brownstone Revival Committee, New York City Mayor Edward I. Koch, Brooklyn Borough President Howard Golden, and U.S. Congressman Leo C. Zeferetti
  - Brownstone correspondence and clippings, 2000-2005 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Series 11: Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella projects, 1967-2008; 10 Linear Feet in nine folders, oversize folders, and five film canisters
  The series documents the Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella projects. Starting in the 1960s, the company purchased and refurbished abandoned brownstones in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn in order to attract new residents to the neighborhood. EGO designed and furnished the interiors of the first Cinderella home at 211 Berkeley Place in 1968, and EHO was vocal proponent of the program. In 1978 the Ortners recieved the company's Cinderella Award, and were featured in Brooklyn Union Gas Company advertisements.
  The series consists of publications, correspondence, films, histories on the program and the company, and ephemera, dating from 1968 to 2008. Of note are three 16mm films produced by the company to promote the program in the 1970s.
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company annual report, 1967 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - 211 Berkeley Place clippings and correspondence to EGO, 1968 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Brooklyn Union, Cinderella, and the Ortners, 1970s-1999 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company, 1970-1976 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Brownstones of Brooklyn films (3 copies), 1972 (Bin 2014.003.11.1-3, Reel -)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella of Berkeley Place (?) film, circa 1972 (Reel 2014.003.11.4, Reel -)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella of Prospect Place film, circa 1972 (Bin 2014.003.11.5, Reel -)
  - Brooklyn Union - Costumes, 1972-1973 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas - Cinderella contact sheet, 1976 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Cinderella project newspaper advertisements, 1976-1977 (Box 75, Folder -)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company - Ortners/Cinderella award winners posters, 1978 (Box 76, Folder -)
  - Brooklyn Union, 1997-1998 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Typescripts on Brooklyn Union Gas Company, Keyspan, and National Grid by EHO, 2006 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Brooklyn Union Gas Company's Cinderella Projects by Elizabeth Soloman, 2008 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    Includes edits by EHO
- Series 12: Historic District Designation Reports, 1969-1973, 2005; 0.3 Linear Feet in nine folders
  Arranged alphabetically.
  The series contains New York City Historic District Designation Reports (1969-1973) and one map of historic locations in the Greenpoint and Williamsburg neighborhoods of Brooklyn (2005). The Ortners were key proponents of the landmarking of the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn, and their photographs of Park Slope buildings were used to support the establishment of the historic district. The series also includes negatives and contact sheets of 272-276 Berkeley Place.
  - Carroll Gardens Historic Designation Report, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Cobble Hill Historic Designation Report, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Greenpoint - Williamsburg Historic Resources Map, 2005 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Greenwich Village Historic Designation Report, 1969 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Park Slope Historic Designation Reports (3 folders), 1973 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    Includes negatives and contact sheets of 272-276 Berkeley Place and other related materials.
  - Stuyvesant Heights Historic Designation Report, 1971 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Upper West Side Historic Designation Reports, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Series 13: Brooklyn and Manhattan postcards, 1873-2007; 0.7 Linear Feet in one small box (Box 52, Folder -)
  The series is divided into Brooklyn postcards, Manhattan postcards, and other postcards.
  The series contains Brooklyn and Manhattan postcards and a small amount of other postcards and tradecards (Rising Sun Stove Polish and Paine's Funiture Manufactory) collected by Everett Ortner, dating from 1873 to 2007.